

Curriculum Vitae for Asmund Ødegård

Personal information

Address: Sneisveien 26 E-mail: asmund@xal.no

1407 Vinterbro Phone: +47 900 69 915 23.08.1972 Nationality: Norwegian

Summary

Born:

I am a senior software developer, project leader, and researcher, with 19 years of professional experience. Most of my career prior to founding Expert Analytics AS together with Ola Skavhaug, has been with Simula Research Laboratory, ranked as Norway's best ICT research institution in 2012. Through various positions in that company I have obtained a broad set of technical and management skills, which I since 2013 has used as Managing Director and Senior Consultant in Expert Analytics. My main areas of technical expertise spans from mathematical software development and scripting, to administration of advanced ICT solutions and configuration management. Both through education and practical hands-on experience I have developed strong analytical skills within my fields of expertise.

As manager and leader of several projects with internal and external participants, I have learned the importance of understanding the strengths and skills of the participants in order to deliver on time. Communication within the team is always key to ensure that everyone have ownership in the project and stay motivated. This must always be balanced with a firm leadership.

Technical skills

Frameworks Google App Engine, Puppet, Numpy, Pandas, SciPy, MPI, React,

Knockout, jQuery, RequireJS, Web.py, Turbogears, Bootstrap, Slim,

Twig, AWS, Azure

Languages Python, C, C++, C#, PHP, Java, Javascript, Bash, Matlab, LATEX,

HTML, Sql, CSS, Scala, Lisp

Tools Linux, OS X, VirtualBox, Vagrant, MySql, Sqlite, NoSqls, Apache,

Nginx, Git, Subversion, CVS, Mercurial, Make, SCons, Autoconf,

buildout

Education

| 2006 | Dr. Scient in Scientific Computing, Faculty of Mathematics and Na- |
|------|--|
| | tural Sciences, University of Oslo. Thesis' title "Applications of high |
| | level software for parallel solution of Partial Differential Equations." |
| 1995 | Cand. Scient in Applied and Industrial Mathematics, Department of |
| | Mathematics, University of Oslo |

Professional experience

| 2013 – | Managing Director and Consultant at Expert Analytics |
|-------------|---|
| 2011 - 2013 | Director of External Research Funding at Simula Research Laboratory |
| 2010 - 2011 | Director of Administration at Simula Research Laboratory |
| 2008 - 2010 | Assistant Director of Administration at Simula Research Laboratory |
| 2004 - 2009 | IT Manager at Simula Research Laboratory |
| 2005 - 2007 | Research Scientist at Simula Research Laboratory |
| 2001 - 2005 | Scientific Programmer at Simula Research Laboratory |
| 2000 - 2001 | Scientific Programmer at Department of Informatics, University of |
| | Oslo |
| 1996 – 1999 | Research Assistant at Department of Informatics, University of Oslo |
| 1996 | Summer intern, SINTEF Applied Mathematics |
| 1993 – 1994 | Assistant teacher, Department of Mathematics, University of Oslo |

Languages

| Liigiisii i luciit | English | Fluent |
|--------------------|---------|--------|
|--------------------|---------|--------|

Norwegian Mother tongue

Personal skills

| | Writing and editing, typesetting & typography, try to learn French |
|------------|---|
| Funding | EU and RCN funding instruments, consortium development, proposal |
| | writing |
| Management | Development and implementation of strategies, guidelines and proce- |
| | dures, lead and encourage staff, personnel follow-up |
| Technology | Extensive knowledge about system administration; always eager to |
| | learn about new frameworks and open source technologies; solution |
| | architect and problem solver |

Some interests and hobbies

Hard Bicycle, motorcycle

Soft Playing clarinet and saxophone, cooking &wine, photography Tech Fonts, typesetting with TEX, computers, gadgets, coding

Extended descriptions of selected projects

Activity Auka/mCASH development Role Senior Python Developer

Staffing 12–15 developers

Description I worked with mCASH, later renamed Auka, in two periods—from

2013–2014 and from February 2016 onwards. My responsibilities in this project included integrations of third-party APIs for user-identification with Norwegian BankID, and development of APIs for access to mCASH resources for external integrators, based on OpenID Connect and Oauth protocols. I was also deeply involved in design and implementation of the transactional engine handling the payments; the core of the mCASH system. This engine connects persons, merchants and banks together, and computes transation fees for involved parties in addition to moving correct amounts. The backend system of mCASH is implemented solely in Python. I have also been involved with other parts of the code base, even javascript frontends implemented with React. The development at mCASH followed the Scrum agile method.

Python, Google app engine, webapp2, Jinja2, Javascript, jQuery,

HTML, Nose tests, Git, Jira.

Activity FrontSystems development
Role Senior Developer and adviser

Staffing 3 developers

Tools

Description FrontSystems is a Norwegian company developing a web-based POS

system. The current system was build on some technologies that are approaching EOL, and my main role was to advise and contribute towards a more modern architecture. This include moving development and deployment to Github and Azure as well as implementing reporting services in POS backend using client-side JS rather than Microsoft

reporting services.

Tools C#, JavaScript, Asp.Net, Knockout, Bootstrap, RequireJS, jQuery,

MSSQL, TeamCity, Git, Azure.

Activity Establishing technical infrastructure of Simula Research Laboratory

Role Project leader and main architect

Staffing Project leader, 4 system administrators, external contractors

Description For the newly created research institute we designed and developed

a full technical infrastructure in the renovated office building at the old airport at Fornebu; office networks, back-end facilities and computer room, telephone systems, printers, servers, etc. Technical requirements, budgetary limitations and practical issues had to be taken into consideration in order to establish a scalable and flexible infrastructure.

Activity Building linux clusters

Role Project manager, lead architect and developer

Staffing 2 additional Systems administrators

Description For the scientific computing group at Ifi, University of Oslo and later at

Simula Research Laboratory, I was in charge of building three different compute clusteres for advanced numerical computations. The systems grew from 32 compute cores up to 576, and was configured with core os, multiple networks, schedulers and queue systems. The first clusters where managed with CFengine as provisioning system, while the last

one was provisioned using Puppet.

Tools Debian GNU/Linux, CFengine, Puppet, OpenPBS, MAUI, MPIch,

BSP,

Activity Outsourcing of ICT services

Role Project coordinator

Description Simula Research Laboratory decided in 2012 to put a contract for its

IT operations out for tender, after running the services with internal resources for a decade. My core responsibility was authoring the specification of the tender and evaluating the offers as well as participate in negotiating the final contract. I was also responsible for handling the communication with all the internal stakeholders. As the change affected the daily work of all employees it was particularly important to have an open and inclusive dialog in the process to ensure a satis-

factory result.

Activity PySE

Role Main developer and researcher

Description Python Stencil Environment (PySE) is a high level environment for

solving partial differential equations using finite difference methods (FDM). The environment provides an abstraction for the stencil concept of FDM, which makes it possible to implement FDM-based simulators in notation very close to the mathematical formulation. The environment is inherently parallell and distributes a problem on the available hardware in an optimal way based on the communication patterns defined by the stencils. PySE was developed as part of my

PhD studies and published as open source software.

Tools Python, Numpy, Scipy, SWIG, C++, MPI

Activity SmartBlikk development

Role Systems Architect and Senior Developer

responsibility was development of an API for the system for import of data from external systems, as well as integrating external APIs for use from SmartBlikk, mainly for importing accounting data. The pilot of SmartBlikk was created by the founder of Intelliview, and I am in charge of designing and implementing the second version of the system with dynamic in-browser reporting capabilities. I am also in charge of establishing a deployment environment for SmartBlikk on the cloud, specifically on Amazon Elastic Beanstalk scaling out with

multiple EC2 nodes and using AWS RDS database.

Tools Php, Mysql, Slim, Twig, Javascript, jQuery, AWS EB, AWS EC2, AWS

RDS.